<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Education on Nilavara</title><link>https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/tags/education/</link><description>Recent content in Education on Nilavara</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Knowledge Acquisition</title><link>https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/knowledge_acquisition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/knowledge_acquisition/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Knowledge acquisition should come in 2 forms - deliberate and free-flowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deliberate knowledge acquisition in 3 fields&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal: Observe our patterns of behavior, and understand whether or not it aligns with goals one has set for himself. Observing oneself also inevitably brings to light one&amp;rsquo;s strengths and weaknesses, and allows the opportunity to experiment with them.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantified self&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mindfulness/Metacognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professional: In real life, one must earn a living. Whether you view your profession in materialistic terms or philosophical terms, It behooves us to do it better. Find your 
&lt;a href="https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/circle_of_competence"&gt;Circle of competence&lt;/a&gt;
 and expand it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiritual/Philosophical: Everybody should deal with questions like what is my purpose, what is my life philosophy, and a tangential set of why&amp;rsquo;s. It is not necessary to find answers to these questions. However, completely avoiding tussles with them might lead to finding ourselves having mislived. See 
&lt;a href="https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/living_in_bad_faith"&gt;Living in bad faith&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What separates knowledge acquisition different from deliberate knowledge acquisition is the portion of time dedicated to 
&lt;a href="https://ibnishak.github.io/digital-garden/metalearning"&gt;Metalearning&lt;/a&gt;
. In addition to acquiring knowledge, one should also evaluate the methods, reasons, and progress of knowledge acquisition ideally at fixed intervals.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>